Man, I can't believe we lost.
（渡）あーあ　負けちまったよ。
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
（渡）全国大会で　優勝して
高校で　国立３連覇。→
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Win Nationals, take my third straight national high-school title,
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
Smaller
Vehicles
May Pass
空前のワタリンフィーバー。→
generate unprecedented Watarin Fever,
reluctantly move to the UK,
後ろ髪　引かれながら　渡英。→
stir up the rumor mill with a model,
モデルと　浮名を流して
リーグ得点王。→
lead the league in goals,
１０年連続　バロンドール。→
and win ten Ballon d'Ors in a row.
順風満帆な人生が
若干　予定が狂っちまった。
My life of smooth sailing...
kinda got derailed.
I botched my chance to become a star.
（渡）スターに　なり損ねちまった。
If you want to be a superstar,
that just comes with the territory.
（公生）スーパースターに
挫折は　付き物だよ。→
It's more dramatic.
ドラマになる。
メッシも　そうだ。
Same thing with Messi.
（渡）じゃ　お前に　ぴったりだ。
Then it's the perfect deal for you.
今期のスターは
お前に譲るよ。　公生。
I'm handing you the starring role this season, Kousei.
（公生）僕は　渡じゃないよ。
I'm not you, Watari.
Damn straight.
（渡）そりゃ　そうだ。
俺は　俺。　お前は　お前。→
I'm not you, either.
俺は　椿の母性を　くすぐれないし
ピアノも　弾けない。
I can't appeal to Tsubaki's maternal instincts,
and I can't play the piano.
まだ　音が？
You still can't hear?
（公生）《怖い》
I'm scared.
頭から　離れないんだ。
I can't get it out of my head.
（公生）《怖い…　怖い》
I'm scared. I'm scared!
また…。
I don't...
音が聞こえなくなるかも
しれないって。
I don't know if I'll ever be able to hear myself play again.
スーパースターに
挫折は　付き物さ。→
If you want to be a superstar,
that just comes with the territory.
逆境でこそ　そいつが
本物か　どうか　分かる。→
Your true character is revealed by your actions in face of adversity.
Or so they say.
だってよ。
（渡）星は　夜　輝くんだぜ。
Stars only shine when they're set against the night.
（観客）《ショパン　『エチュード
作品２５－５』って…》
This is Chopin's Etude Op. 25, No. 5, isn't it?
（観客）《こんな曲だったけ？》
（観客）《速いし　荒い》
Did it really go like this?
It's so fast and rough.
（椿）《かをちゃんの
伴奏したときと同じ》→
It's just like his accompaniment with Kao.
《音が　でこぼこ。
どんどん　速くなってく》
The notes are all over the place.
And he's only getting faster and faster.
《まただ…》
Here we go again.
《響いてこない》
It's not ringing.
《ピアノの音が…》
The sound of the piano...
《音が…》
The sound...
《深海に　のみ込まれてゆく》
I'm about to drown in a deep sea.
《まだだ…　集中　集中　集中！》
Not yet!
Focus, focus, focus!
《全神経を　ピアノに傾けろ！》
Give the piano your undivided attention!
《あのときのように》
Just like you did with her.
《全身で　音を　つかめ！》
Grasp the notes with your whole body!
（早希）《これは　罰なのよ》→
This is your punishment...
《公生。　私を…　私の夢を→
Kousei.
This is what you get for rejecting me.
For rejecting my dream.
あなたが拒絶した　罰》
（早希）《分かるでしょ？》
You understand that, don't you?
（観客）《下手くそだ》
He's atrocious.
Don't tell me he can't...
（高柳）《有馬。　まさか　音が…》
（井端）
《これでは　耳障りでしかない》
This is simply grating to the ears!
（絵見）《有馬…》→
Arima.
《出だしは　一音も　漏らさず
完璧に　弾けていたのに》
You were able to play the opening without a missing a single note.
《音が　とれないせい？》→
Can you not perceive the sound?
《音が聞こえないのは
ホント？》→
Is it true that you can't hear your own playing?
《だって　これは
苦しみに　あふれている音だ》
Because this is the sound of someone writhing in agony.
《音が聞こえなくても　分かる。
細胞が　わめいてる》
Even if I can't hear my own sound, I can tell.
Every cell in my body is screaming out.
《こんなの　ショパンじゃない》
This isn't Chopin!
（早希）《これは　罰なのよ》
《違う！》
This is your punishment.
You're wrong!
（早希）《音に　見放されてるのよ》《違う！》
The notes have abandoned you.
You're wrong!
《僕は　お母さんのために
一生懸命　やったじゃないか》
I worked so hard just for you, Mom!
（早希）
《ピアノは　あなた自身よ》→
The piano is you.
《たたいても　たたいても
答えては　くれないでしょ？》→
Pound away at it all you want, but it won't answer you, will it?
《孤独なのは…
独りぼっちなのは…》
The reason you are lonely...
The reason you are all alone...
《お前なんか
死んじゃえばいいんだ》
I wish you would just die.
（早希）《あなたの　罰》
That is your punishment.
《やめちゃおうかな》
Maybe I should just stop.
（絵見）《音から　緊張感が
失われていく》
The tension is fading away from his playing.
《途中で　やめる気？》
Is he planning to stop midway?
《やっぱり　僕は　僕のまま》
I haven't really changed at all.
《あのときのようになんて
虫が　よすぎたのかな》
I can't play like I did before.
Was it all just wishful thinking?
《コンクールに出れば
何かが変わると　思っていた》
I thought something would change if I entered this competition.
《でも　僕は　僕のまま
何も変わらない》
But I'm still the same.
Nothing's changed.
（かをり）《駄目…　やめないで！》
No!
Don't stop!
（観客）これ…　演奏　やめちゃうぞ。
He's...
He's going to stop playing.
（観客）あの　有馬が…。
Arima, of all people...
（観客）傷口が　広がるよりは…。
Better to just cut his losses.
《やめるな！　続けて！》
Don't stop! Keep playing!
（椿）《やめちゃ　駄目！》
You can't stop!
《これ　見て。
君のエントリーナンバー》
Look at this.
Your entry number.
《ケッヘル　２６５番　モーツァルト
『キラキラ星　変奏曲』》
Köchel No. 265: Mozart's Twinkle, Twinkle, Little Star.
《星は　君の頭上に　輝くよ！》
The stars are shining down on you!
（武士）《頼むよ。　冗談だろ？
これが　あの有馬かよ？》→
Come on. You gotta be kidding me.
Is this the Arima I know?
《完全無欠　正確無比。
見る影もない》→
Absolute perfection, unmatched accuracy.
He's just a shadow of his former self—
《俺の憧れた　有馬　公生》
the one I used to look up to.
《俺の２年間は
何だったんだよ？》
What were these two years for?
Tell me this is just a joke...
もう…　冗談やめてくれよ。
本当に…。
He really...
（観客）演奏　やめちゃった。
stopped playing.
Your Lie in April
（観客）天才も　地に落ちたか。
So the prodigy has fallen back to Earth?
（観客）どうなるの？
（観客）失格。　無評価だよ。
What happens now?
Disqualification. He won't be evaluated.
（井端）《フンッ　終わりだ》
It's over.
Sumiya Junior High
Arima Kousei
Past Accolades
Moriwaki Student Competition - Piano Division
Houllier International Competition
Saiki Competition
Sumiya Junior High
Arima Kousei
Past Accolades
Moriwaki Student Competition - Piano Division
（観客）どんな理由でも
演奏を中断したら→
Arima Kousei
Sumiya Junior High
Past Accolades
Moriwaki Student Competition - Piano Division
Regardless of the reason, if you cut your performance short,
Arima Kousei
Sumiya Junior High
Past Accolades
Arima Kousei
Sumiya Junior High
そいつのコンクールは　もう…。
the competition is over for you.
《あーあ　終わっちゃったな》
Oh, man.
I've really done it now.
＜二の舞い。　同じ穴のむじな。
類は　友を呼ぶ＞
Here we go again.
Two of a kind. Birds of a feather.
＜あのとき　演奏を中断した瞬間
君のコンクールは　終わった＞
The moment I stopped playing that day,
the competition was over for you.
＜君は　何のために
バイオリンを弾いたんだろう＞
What exactly were you playing for?
＜容赦のない人だ。
何を見ても　君を思い出す＞
You're so merciless.
Every little thing I see reminds me of you.
＜本当に　容赦のない人だ＞
You really have no mercy.
＜僕の中にいる　君ですら…＞
Even the part of you that resounds within me.
＜諦めることを許してくれない＞
You won't let me give up.
＜あのとき　君は　何のために
バイオリンを弾いたのかな＞
I wonder...
I wonder what you were playing for at that moment.
《アゲイン！》
Again!
《弾き直し！？》
He started playing again?
Doesn't matter.
《駄目だ。　弾き直したところで
テンポが　揃ってない》
He might've started again, but the tempo's uneven.
《大切なのは　イメージ》
What's important is how you visualize it.
《君は　この曲を
どう弾きたい？》
How do you want to play this piece?
《誰のために　弾きたい？》
Who do you want to play it for?
＜あのとき　君は　何のため
誰のために　弾いたのかな＞
That day...
What were you playing for? Who were you playing for?
《友人Ａ。　君がいいの》
Friend A.
I want you.
《僕は　音が聞こえないんだ》
I can't hear the sound of the piano.
I hereby appoint you as my accompanist.
《君を　私の伴奏者に任命します》
＜ああ…　そうだ＞
Oh.
That's it.
僕は　君のために弾こう。
I'll play for you.
（高柳）
《また演奏が　変わり始めた》→
His playing is changing yet again.
《出だしは　コンピューターのように
無機質で　譜面どおりに正確に》→
The opening was as robotic as a computer,
matching the score down to the last note.
《途中から　泣きじゃくる　子供が
鍵盤を　たたきつけるように》→
Halfway through, it felt like a sobbing child was pounding the keys.
《三度　その姿を変える》
This makes three times that he's transformed.
What just happened to him?
《あいつに　何が起こったんだ？》
《この変わりよう　半端ねえ》→
This transformation is unreal.
《３人の演奏者が
弾いてるみたいだ》
It's like there were three different pianists playing.
（絵見）《演奏が　変わるどころか
音が　変わる》
It's not only his playing that's changed.
It's the entire sound.
《音が　きらめきだす！》
His notes...
are starting to sparkle.
《演奏を中断しちゃった》
I stopped playing midway.
I'll be disqualified.
《失格だな。
暴虐非道な　誰かと一緒だ》
Just like a certain ruthless tyrant I know.
《星は　君の頭上に　輝くよ！》
The stars are shining down on you.
《ありったけの君で
真摯に弾けば　いいんだよ》
Just play with sincerity, and put your all into giving the performance of a lifetime!
《本当の君は
ショパンを　どう弾きたい？》
How do you really want to play Chopin?
《私たちは
ショパンじゃないもん》
We don't have to aspire to be Chopin.
《君は　どうせ　君だよ》
You're you.
The conversations we've shared are shining down on me like stars in the night.
《君と交わした言葉　一つ一つが
星のように　降り注いでくる》
《一人で見た空は
のみ込まれそうで　怖かった》
I was so afraid of being swallowed up by the sky when I looked at it alone.
《渡と見た星空は　移り気で→
The view I saw with Watari seemed so carefree,
椿と見た星空は
底抜けに輝いて　どこか不安げで》
and the one I saw with Tsubaki was bursting with so much radiance that I actually felt anxious.
《君と見る星空は　どんなだろう》
I wonder what I'll see in the sky when I gaze at it with you.
（絵見）
チョークのにおいがする。→
The smell of chalk.
不細工に　ひび割れた　窓ガラス。
遠くから　運動部の声。→
A window with unsightly cracks.
Echoes from distant sports teams.
桜の花びらの影。
かすかな　寝息。
The shadows of cherry blossom petals.
The faint breathing of a sleeping girl.
（絵見）風景が　変わる。→
The scenery is changing.
これは　有馬のイメージ。
This is Arima's imagery.
（絵見）
《有馬の世界に　埋没してゆく》
Everyone is being immersed in Arima's world.
《満足のいく　演奏は
できないかもしれない》
We might not be able to give a performance we can live with.
But we're going to play.
《でも　弾くの。　弾ける機会と→
As long as there's an opportunity and an audience that will listen.
聴いてくれる人がいるなら
私は　全力で弾く》
I'm gonna play with everything I've got.
See me for who I truly am!
《どうだ！　これが俺だ！》
Let it ring! Let it ring!
《響け！　響け！》
《聴いてくれた人が
私を忘れないように》
That way, the people who listen will never forget me,
and I'll have a place in their hearts forever.
《その人の心に
ずっと　住めるように》
《僕は　たった一人で　いいや》
There's only one who matters to me.
《君だけで　いいや》
You're the only one.
《ありがとう　ありがとう
ありがとう　ありがとう》
Thank you.
《ありがとう》
（観客）《これが　あの有馬？》
Is this really the same person?
（女の子）《どうしてだろう。
我慢しないと　泣いちゃいそう》
What's going on?
If I don't hold back, I think I'm gonna cry.
（落合）《もう　年かしらね》→
I suppose I'm getting old.
Hearing such honest emotions puts an ache in my heart.
《いちずな思いを聞かされると
切なくなる》
《戻ってこい　戻ってこい》→
Come back.
Come back...
《有馬！》
Arima!
I can hear her soft breathing as she sleeps.
《かすかな寝息が　聞こえる》
Like a cat's.
《猫みたいだ》
《迷い込んだ　一枚の花びら》
A single petal that sailed into my life.
《最悪の第一印象》
The worst first impression ever.
《友達を好きな　女の子》
The girl who likes my best friend.
Will it reach her?
《届くかな？　届くといいな》
I can only hope so.
He's finally back.
（かをり）やっと　帰ってきた。
《僕の中に　君がいる》
You're a part of me now.
《君がいる！》
You're here.
君がいるよ。
You're here...
有馬　公生君。
Arima Kousei!
（黒猫）
《あの子の言ったとおりだ》→
She was right.
《音楽は　自由だ》
Music is freedom.
（黒猫）《君は　自由なんだ》
You're free.
（観客）えっと…。
（観客）そうか　拍手だ。
Um...
Oh, right. We should probably applaud.
（観客）何？　これ。
（観客）よかったの？　悪かったの？
What was that?
Was that good?
Or was it bad?
《そりゃあ　誰だって　戸惑うぜ》
That was enough to throw anyone off.
《これを
どう評価しろっていうんだ》
How am I supposed to evaluate something like that?
《これは　余韻？
変遷の途中？》→
Is it resonating?
Is he transitioning?
《何かの前兆？》
Is this some kind of omen?
《まったく…》→
Man...
《後悔なんて　みじんもない顔だ》
Not the slightest trace of regret on that face.
《なしのつぶて。
まぁ　そうだよな》
No feedback.
Well, of course not.
《僕は　たった一人で　いいんだ》
There's only one person who matters to me.
《届くかな？》
Will it reach her?
《届くといいな》
I can only hope so.
Episode 10
The Scene We Shared
Even when I'm down, you know how to put a smile on my face
ochikondeta toki mo ki ga tsukeba waratteru
The whole world comes back to life when I'm with you
futari nara sekai wa iki wo fukigaeshita
Through the moments that we've shared
onaji jikan wo wakeainagara
and every last miracle that we've cherished
futari de sugoseta kiseki wo
I can only hope this scene of ours will last forever
korekara saki mo tsunagetainda
I want to look into your eyes and say
chanto me wo mite tsutaetai
Your voice is the only sound I want to hear
kiiteitai koe wa kimi no mono datta yo
Wrapping me in your embrace with just a whisper in my ear
mimi wo tsutai karadajuu wo tsutsumu you na
That's how your voice makes me feel
sono koe datta
No one else can compare, you are the only one for me
hoka no daredemo nai kimi janakya dame da yo
I realized I never want to leave your side
itsumademo soba ni itai to omoeta
Episode 11
The Light Within
I realized I never want to leave your side
itsumademo soba ni itai to omoeta
Episode 11
The Light Within
（井端）もう　不愉快だ！
けしからん！→
That was offensive!
Outrageous!
Could he have been less prepared?!
練習不足も　甚だしい！
（審査員）先生　しーっ。
Settle down, sir!
（絵見）《おっしゃるとおり。
本当に　ど下手》→
He's not wrong.
That really sucked.
《譜面を　きちんと
さらったのかしら》→
I wonder if he even studied the sheet music properly.
《でも　あいつの音は
４月の気配がした》
Still, those notes of his...
It felt like being in the height of spring.
（落合）有馬君って…。
Arima.
面白い子ね。　ウフッ。
He's an interesting boy, isn't he?
（落合）《操り人形が
糸を断って　自立し始めた》→
The puppet has severed his strings and start to walk on his own.
Of course, those newfound emotions do
seem to be a bit much for him to handle.
《もっとも
突然　手に入れた感情を→
持て余し気味だけどね》
どうしちゃったんだろう。
（観客）あの　天才　有馬が。
What could've happened to him?
To think he was such a prodigy...
（紘子）ふ～ん　やるじゃん。
Not bad...
凡才。
Mr. Mediocre.